All right, Andrew, I want to ask you
about peptides.
All the rage. You look at Google Trends.
Everybody and their brother has a
peptide startup, but there seems to
maybe be something there. I don't know
if there's a there there. For people who
have heard the word, don't know exactly
what folks are talking about. I get
texted every week multiple times from
people asking about various peptides.
And I'd say half the time, depending on
what they're trying to do, I'm like,
"Can't you just be a grown-up and inject
testosterone or HGH [laughter]
instead?" If you're trying to get there
directly. But I would be very interested
here. I know there's a broad spectrum of
stuff that people are experimenting
with.
What are these things? And And what's
what's your current thinking?
>> I also don't completely disagree with
you about like just be a grown-up and
take cypionate and HGH. If you want to
maintain fertility, take some HCG as
well.
>> Yeah.
>> And I'm being facetious, of course. I I
think there are risks to all of those,
but
it is the appropriate opening joke
/reality, because if you're expecting
cypionate HGH type results from
peptides,
you ain't going to get them. At least
not with respect to like anabolic
growth, feelings of well-being.
Peptides are short chains of amino
acids. Insulin's a peptide, etc. I
cannot take credit for what I'm about to
say next, but it's a very, very
important principle. Like this is kind
of the theme today, I suppose.
Abubakr who's an MD came on the podcast,
talked about peptides, and he said,
"Look, for many, many
hundreds, if not thousands, of years,
but certainly hundreds of years in the
context of pharma,
people have been searching for medicines
in plants.
Isolating medicines from plants. Pharma
companies still do this.
Now, people are starting to look for
medicines within the body. And peptides
are a great example of that. GLP, for
instance. The drugs that increase GLP do
so to thousandfold levels over the
levels of circulating GLP that you would
have.
And they result in, as we all know,
robust weight loss.
So, that's one category. I think we need
to think about categories of peptides,
but understand that peptides are all
over They're made in your brain and
body. Some of them may have benefits
when
made synthetically and delivered at
very, very high doses,
such as with these GLP agonists,
Ozempic, Mounjaro. Retatrutide is one
that we should talk about, made by
Lilly. It's coming out soon.
It impacts the GLP system, but also the
GIP and the glucagon system.
>> Careful with that one, kid us.
>> A lot of people are going to be
microdosing it.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, a lot of people are finding that
microdoses can have similar effects, and
that's an important kind of cost-risk
analysis. Okay, so stepping back,
peptides are made in your body. They at
high concentrations made synthetically,
they may provide
benefits that are make them medicines.
So, we can think of the weight loss
peptides,
the GLPs being the most prominent
example. The GLP drugs that increased
levels of GLP hundredfold were used to
treat diabetes for a while.
Still are.
But they didn't induce much weight loss.
The ones that
raise GLP levels thousandfold
or more, those lead to robust weight
loss, including muscle loss, and so
that's part of the controversy. Also,
there's discussion about maybe
increasing some apathy. They reduced
craving for alcohol and perhaps cravings
more generally. At the recommended
dosages, in some people they can create
nausea, which is why some people are
taking less of them and still getting
the weight loss benefits, but less
nausea. There's a lot of stuff going on
there, but to stay on the GLPs and
weight loss peptides specifically, Lilly
developed retatrutide, which hits the
GLP, GIP, and glucagon system, leads to
the most robust weight loss, seems to
spare some muscle, perhaps. People
should always resistance train anyway to
offset that, but
it's the most effective of those weight
loss
let's just call it GLPs even though it
hits these other systems. The gray
market is
the quote unquote for research purposes
only stuff that you can buy online. It's
perfectly legal to sell
for research purposes only not for
animal or human use. And I joked on X a
while ago like wow, all these home labs,
everyone's buying this. Of course people
are injecting them. The concern is about
contamination with things like
lipopolysaccharide or you're not getting
what you think you're getting. So, many
people are already taking retatrutide
even though it hasn't been formally
released
because it's pretty easy to synthesize.
And so it's being sold on the gray
market. People are taking it. There's a
second category and then I'll return to
the kind of gray market issue. The
second category would be things to
increase growth hormone. So called
growth hormone secretagogues, things
like sermorelin, ipamorelin,
tesamorelin.
These are all variants on the theme of
get the brain neurons that project down
to the pituitary to stimulate release of
growth hormone at night. Typically you
don't need a couple hours before sleep
is the idea. Probably good for sleep
anyway. It is good for sleep anyway.
Then you inject this stuff. Typically it
leads to maybe a
three to eightfold increase in
growth hormone IGF-1.
Some stimulate appetite quite a bit like
MK-677, some don't.
I've tried sermorelin very briefly.
Dramatically increased my slow wave deep
sleep, nuked my REM sleep. This is a
common theme. Spiked my prostate
specific antigen. I've never had any
problems with PSA. I came off it, PSA
went back to normal. No one's been able
to give me a mechanistic explanation for
that. I'm not about to run the
experiment again. I didn't find that I
got much fat loss from it, but I didn't
use it very long. I didn't find I got
stronger.
You know, just didn't seem worth it to
me
given the PSA thing. A lot of people
take these thinking they're going to get
these really dramatic increases in
growth hormone.
They sound dramatic, three to eightfold,
but whether or not they're meaningful in
terms of fat loss, it doesn't really
seem they're that robust, especially
given that you have all the GLPs now.
So, the growth hormone secretagogues
also include things like CJC,
and there's some variants on these,
which can lead to some insulin
resistance, but maybe spikes GH a bit
more.
I don't [clears throat] know. None of
those, to me, really seem worth it,
personally. Just given the effects
aren't that great.
You know, if someone can afford it and
they can get a script for it, probably
better to just take pharma-grade
somatropin or omnitrope growth hormone.
And, you know, the bodybuilders would
take like eight IUs a day or something
crazy like that. But, the in the trials
that have been done with metformin and
GH, typically, it's people are taking
one to two IUs five nights per week.
That will dramatically increase deep
sleep and probably sleep overall, and
the effects on fat loss and just tissue
repair, healing, and feelings of
well-being, and just cognitive function,
anecdotally, people and subjectively,
people say like, "Wow, I just feel so
great." This is the getting up in the
morning and be like, "Wow, my joints
feel good." and just being ready to like
go, go, go. It's not anabolic as much as
something like testosterone, etc. But,
I'm not telling people to run out and do
GH, but if you could get a good script a
script for real GH and take a low dose
versus taking a bunch of like unknown
secretagogue peptides, that seems like
an obvious one for me.
Then, there's a category of things like
BPC 157, body protection compound 157,
which is
a amino acid chain that is in gastric
juice, but it's this isolated amino acid
chain that
seems to be the one that's most popular.
And, at the same time, it's the one for
which most people
probably taking it for all the wrong
reasons. I've tried it. I definitely
feel like after a pain or strain, the
recovery is faster.
But, I can't do the control experiment
cuz it goes systemic. So, it's not like
you could have Let's say you hurt both
biceps. You could You can't inject into
one bicep and not the other and assume
that it's just acting locally. It's
going to go systemically. There are
capsule forms of BPC that people claim
are just as good. I don't know.
Do you have to inject locally close to
the injury? It seems that might be
helpful. The animal data on BPC are
really impressive.
Cartilage regrowth, fibroblast
migration, angiogenesis, nerve regrowth.
It's a literature I've spent a lot of
time with. There's not a single
published human trial.
Where I think the most interesting use
of it perhaps is
is I know someone recently, she wrote to
me and she said that her dog had a
spinal injury. And she said, "Does BPC
work in animals?" I go, "Actually,
pretty much all the data are in animals.
So, if my dog, God forbid, had an
injury,
I'd be
willing to give him or her [snorts] BPC.
You have to work out the appropriate
dosage.
>> How would you source that?
Hypothetically.
>> So, you can get it from compounding
pharmacies now. So, you need a doctor to
write that script.
Depending on your risk tolerance, you
could go to the gray market for research
purposes only. I wouldn't do that.
Peptide Sciences shuttered
their doors, windows, whatever. They
closed a few months back. They they
sensed the heat coming on and they're
like, "We're out." They took their money
and they're out. Smart move, Peptide
Sciences.
So, nowadays you can find doctors that
will prescribe it. And there's also
pentadecapeptide, which is just a
different
form of BPC. Seems to have
same function.
It's easier to find. And getting it from
a compounding pharmacy, of course,
compounding pharmacy is very in
stringency, but is going to be cleaner
than the gray market sourcing, of
course. But, I've no relationship to
these pharmacies, but for instance,
Tailor Made, Upstate, Revive Pharmacy,
these are kind of the better known and
trusted compounding pharmacies.
Compounding pharmacies were allowed to
compound drugs that are still under
patent during shortages.
And
can compound generic drugs. They'll also
truly compound peptides. You could can
get BPC with another one, the TB500.
So-called Wolverine stack. I don't know.
I've never tried TB500. I keep some BPC
157 in the fridge. If I have a a strain
on a joint
>> in for a second? Like the challenge with
so much of this stuff is you can't do
the control.
>> Can't do the control.
>> took the Wolverine stack after I had
elbow surgery and I'm like
Did it help?
>> I have no idea. Frankly, I have no idea.
>> You know what? I will say this, I've
used it a few times, very short runs of
it. I'm not interested in using it as a
general recovery tool or every day or
any I don't have any gut issues. Like so
people have used high doses of BPC to
resolve gut issues. That was the
original use. You know, in this clinical
trial they did BPC enemas at very high
dosages.
>> Sounds like an Austin party.
>> You know, and supposedly, I learned this
from Abood, Pavlov actually had a side
gig. He was a health influencer. He'd
give people gastric juices to try and
resolve ulcers and things like that. And
we know gastric juices contain a number
of beneficial peptides.
But I don't recommend
>> they down those? How did they get them
in there?
>> How they down them and how they get them
>> Shots glass of gastric juices?
>> maybe he had a cabinet of people with a
you know, they're tapping them. Yeah, so
they're rough. So, you know, people say
should I take BPC 157? No, you shouldn't
unless you have an injury or maybe in
that case you get clean compounded
pharmacy BPC and you inject it locally
or you take it systemically. You try it,
see if it helps. But why would you take
it ongoing? That just doesn't make any
sense to me. It doesn't make any sense
to me, frankly. And again, you go back
to your sort of half joke at the
beginning, you really want to recover
quickly from exercise? Take an IU or two
IUs of
GH every night before sleep and you will
recover magnificently well.